Register of the Robert Charles Mardian papers, 1957-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Charles Mardian papers
1957-1995
79102
Hoover Institution Archives
82 manuscript boxes, 7 videotape cassettes (34.9 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, proposals, minutes, testimony, legal documents, printed matter, and audiovisual material relating to education policy during the presidential administration of Richard M. Nixon, school desegregation, surveillance of radical movements, administration of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and the Watergate affair and subsequent trials. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Mardian, Robert Charles, 1923-2006
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
1923 October 23 Born, Pasadena, California
1949-1969 Attorney, Pasadena, California
1968-1969 Member, U.S. Presidential Transition Team
1969-1970 General Counsel, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
1970-1971 Executive Director, Cabinet Committee on Education
1970-1972 Assistant Attorney General, U.S. Department of Justice, Internal Security Division
1972-1973 Political Coordinator, Committee to Re-elect the President
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; United States. Department of Health, Education and Welfare.; United States. Department of Justice.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Education--United States.; Education.; Justice, Administration of--United States.; Radicalism--United States.; School integration--United States.; Subversive activities--United States.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Race relations.; Video tapes.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.
- Speeches and Writings, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Draft and final copies of speeches and articles, memoranda, clippings, and other printed material. Primarily relates to school desegregation and Nixon Administration policies. Arranged chronologically.
  - General (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1969 (Folder 2)
  - 1970 (Folder 3)
  - 1971 (Folder 4)
  - 1972 (Folder 5)
- Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1957-1970 (Boxes 1-6)
  Speeches, memoranda, reports, clippings, correspondence, notes, printed articles, legal documents, newsletters, statutes and regulations, school desegregation plans, legislative proposals, and miscellany. Primarily relates to school desegregation. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - Memoranda and correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - White House communications. Correspondence, memoranda, legal documents, speech transcript, and clippings, 1968-1970 (Folder 7)
  - Austin Geriatrics. Material relating to a disputed transfer of government property (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Civil rights
    - General
      - Notes. Also includes draft and final copies of a speech, and memoranda (Folder 7)
      - Statements
        - Robert Finch and John Mitchell, 1969 July 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Robert Finch testimony relating to the Emergency School Aid Act of 1970 (Folder 2)
        - Jerris Leonard, Select Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity, 1970 July 13 (Folder 3)
        - Admiral Hyman Rickover, House Committee on Education and Labor, 1970 June 6 (Folder 4)
    - Legislative histories of Titles IV and VI (Folder 5)
    - Model cities (Folder 6)
    - National Education Association (Folder 7)
    - Tax exempt status (Folder 8)
    - Title VI. Relates to non-discrimination in federally-asisted programs, primarily school desegregation
      - General (Folder 9-10)
      - Alabama (Folder 11)
      - Arkansas (Folder 12)
      - California (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Enforcement proceedings (Folder 2)
      - Florida
        - General (Folder 3)
        - U.S. v. Taylor County, Florida (Folder 4)
      - Georgia (Folder 5)
      - Guidelines. Relates to policy (Folder 6)
      - Head Start Program (Folder 7)
      - Higher education (Folder 8-9)
      - Legislation
        - General (Folder 10)
        - Desegregation assistance to school districts (Folder 11-12)
      - Litigation (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
      - Louisiana (Folder 3)
      - Mexican Americans (Folder 4)
      - Michigan (Folder 5)
      - Mississippi (Folder 6)
      - New York (Folder 7)
      - North Carolina (Folder 8)
      - Northern schools (Folder 9)
      - Regulation (Folder 10)
      - Reverse discrimination (Folder 11)
      - Schools, 1969 (Folder 12)
      - South Carolina
        - General (Folder 13)
        - Abbeville (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Supreme Court decisions (Folder 2)
      - Texas (Folder 3)
      - Virginia (Folder 4)
  - Federal employees
    - Thursday Discussion Group (Folder 5-6)
    - Federal Employees for a Democratic Society (Folder 7)
    - Vietnam moratorium committees (Folder 8)
  - Office of Equal Opportunity (Folder 9)
  - Social Security Division. Correspondence (Folder 10)
  - Welfare
    - General. AFDC program, Medicaid, and other miscellany (Folder 11-12)
    - Legal cases
      - Rosado v. Wyman. Relates to the welfare program in New York (Folder 13)
      - Dandridge v. Williams. Relates to the welfare program in Maryland (Folder 14)
- Cabinet Committee on Education, 1969-1970 (Boxes 6-11)
  Memoranda, reports, statements (including Richard Nixon), press releases, clippings, correspondence, agenda and minutes, legislative proposals, and a petition. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - General. Includes material relating to consultants, a conference in Atlanta, and a videotape production (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - General (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
    - History (Folder 4)
    - Legislation (Folder 5-6)
    - Meetings
      - General. Includes meetings with concerned mothers, Mississippi officials, and state governors (Folder 7-9)
      - Committee meetings
        - 1970 March-May (Folder 10-15)
        - 1970 June-Oct. (Box 8, Folder 1-10)
    - Newsletter ("Infoflow") (Folder 11)
    - Presidential documents. Weekly compilations (Folder 12)
    - Press releases (Folder 13)
    - Reports
      - Frederick Mosteller and Daniel P. Moynihan (eds.), "On Equality of Educational Opportunity" (Folder 14)
      - South Carolina school desegregation (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Statements
      - Testimony of Wilmer S. Cody, Select Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity, 1970 June 23 (Folder 2)
      - Statement by Richard Nixon on desegregation (Folder 3)
  - Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW) Desegregation Work Group (Folder 4)
  - Departments of Justice and HEW Task Force (Folder 5)
  - Desegregation court order and voluntary plan (Folder 6)
  - Emergency School Aid Act of, 1970 (Folder 7)
  - Emergency School Aid Act of, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Emergency School Assistance Program - briefing material (Folder 2-3)
  - Information center (Folder 4)
  - Knowledge survey (Folder 5-7)
  - Majority-black school districts (Folder 8)
  - State Advisory Committees
    - General
      - Weekly State Advisory Committee activity report (Folder 9)
      - Memoranda to State Advisory Committee, 1970 July (Folder 10)
    - Alabama (Folder 11)
    - Arkansas (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Georgia (Folder 2)
    - Louisiana (Folder 3)
    - Mississippi (Folder 4)
    - North Carolina (Folder 5)
    - South Carolina (Folder 6)
- Department of Justice, 1967-1978 (Boxes 11-18)
  Notes, affidavits, briefs and other legal documents, transcripts, memoranda, reports, correspondence, newsletters, pamphlets, and clippings. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General. Legal documents, primarily briefs (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
  - Berrigan, Daniel and Philip. Clippings (Folder 9)
  - Black Panthers. Clippings (Folder 10)
  - Camden, N.J. Clippings relating to draft board arrests (Folder 11)
  - Capitol bombing. Clippings (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Espionage. Clippings (Folder 2)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI)
    - General. Clippings (Folder 3)
    - Hoover, J. Edgar. Primarily memoranda (Folder 4)
    - Internal Security Division (Folder 5)
    - Sullivan, William. Correspondence and a serial issue, 1971-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Grand juries. Clippings (Folder 7)
  - Jewish Defense League. Clippings (Folder 8)
  - Kent State. Clippings (Folder 9)
  - Kleindienst, Richard G. Relates to his nomination for Attorney General
    - General. Clippings (Folder 10-11)
    - General. Clippings (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Hearings. Primarily relates to the ITT investigation; includes notes, memoranda, statements, and correspondence (Folder 2-4)
    - Hearings (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Korean-American relations. Primarily memoranda relating to investigations (Folder 3)
  - Mardian, Robert. Clippings (Folder 4-6)
  - May demonstrations. Clippings (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
  - Mitchell, John M. Clippings (Folder 5)
  - Pentagon papers. Clippings
    - 1971 June 10-July 4 (Folder 6-10)
    - 1971 July 15-1972 April (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Security index. Clippings (Folder 3)
  - Subpoenas. Clippings relating to subpoenas of reporters (Folder 4)
  - Subversive Activities Control Board. Clippings (Folder 5)
  - Wiretapping and electronic eavesdropping. Clippings (Folder 6)
  - Surveillance. Clippings and a Senate hearing transcript relating to surveillance of civilians (Folder 7)
  - U.S. v. Ferguson (Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals) (Folder 8-9)
  - U.S. v. Ferguson (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
  - U.S. v. U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Maryland (Folder 3-4)
  - U.S. v. U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Maryland (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Wilson, Will R. Clippings (Folder 2)
- Watergate, 1970-1975 (Boxes 18-24)
  Legal documents, correspondence, transcripts, interviews, press releases, wire reports and press summaries, bulletins, serial issues, clippings, notes, and printed material. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - General. Serial issues relating to the Nixon administration, 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Senate Select Committee. Mardian testimony, 1973 (Folder 4)
  - Break-in and related litigation
    - General. Correspondence, press releases, memoranda, report, and printed material (Folder 5)
    - Clippings and press material (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
    - Legal documents (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Trial
    - General (Folder 2)
    - Chronology (Folder 3)
    - Clippings and press material. Includes serial issues, wire reports, and press summaries
      - 1974 Oct. (Folder 4-5)
      - 1974 Nov.-Dec. (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
      - 1975 Jan. (Box 22, Folder 1-3)
    - Preparatory material. Correspondence, notes, clippings, memoranda, and legal documents (Folder 4-6)
    - Preparatory material (Box 23, Folder 1-13)
    - Testimony transcripts
      - General. Grand Jury
        - Bittman, William O. (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
        - Mardian, Robert (Folder 4-5)
      - Mardian, Robert (Folder 6)
- Ginsburg, Feldman, and Press Legal Files, 1973-1985 (Boxes 25-72)
  Legal documents, reports, correspondence, hearing and testimony transcripts, printed material, memoranda, statements, notes, and miscellany. The material relates to the trial of Mitchell, et al., for Watergate offenses, the appeal of Mardian's conviction, and a subsequent claim by him against the 1972 campaign liquidation trust. Arranged by case in the order established by the law firm representing Robert Mardian.
  - Watergate trial (Case #2623)
    - General. Miscellaneous documents (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
    - Case summary (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Mardian pleadings
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Exhibits
        - 14-21 (Folder 3-4)
        - 23-52 (Box 27, Folder 1-4)
        - 53-73 (Box 28, Folder 1-4)
        - 71-73 (contd.) (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
    - Mardian prior testimony
      - FBI-SSC interviews and index (Folder 3)
      - Grand Jury, 1973 May 7 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Ervin Committee, 1973 July 19-20 (Folder 2)
      - Grand Jury, 1973 Aug. 2 and 16 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Other prior testimony
      - E. Howard Hunt (Folder 2-4)
      - E. Howard Hunt (contd.) (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Overt Acts book (Folder 2-4)
    - Overt Acts book (contd.) (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
    - Jury selection (Folder 3)
    - Mardian pleadings. Comments by Mardian (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Preparatory notes on witnesses (Folder 2)
    - Preparatory notes on witnesses (contd.) (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Preparatory trial notes (Folder 2)
    - Pertinent testimony excerpts (Folder 3)
    - List of tapes supplied (Folder 4)
    - Tapes referring to Robert Mardian (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Transcripts of tapes
      - 1-12A (Folder 2)
      - 13-18A (Box 37, Folder 1)
      - 50-61 (Folder 2)
      - 50-61 (contd.) (Box 38, Folder 1)
      - 62-71 (Folder 2-3)
    - Exhibits
      - Mardian, Robert C. (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Ehrlichman, John (Folder 2)
      - Haldeman, Harry R. (Folder 3)
      - Parkinson, Kenneth W. (Folder 4)
      - Mitchell, John (Folder 5)
    - Pretrial pleadings
      - Government (Folder 6)
      - Government (contd.) (Box 40, Folder 1)
      - Mardian (Folder 2)
      - Other defendants (Box 41, Folder 1-2)
      - Other defendants (contd.) (Box 42, Folder 1-4)
    - Trial pleadings
      - Government (Box 43, Folder 1-2)
      - Mardian (Folder 3)
      - Other defendants (Folder 4)
    - Post-trial pleadings
      - Government (Folder 5)
      - Mardian (Box 44, Folder 1)
      - Other defendants (Folder 2)
    - Court of Appeals pleadings (SEE ALSO: Case #1194)
      - Mardian (Folder 3-4)
      - Other defendants (Folder 5)
      - Government (Folder 6)
    - Supreme Court pleadings (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Motion for judgment of acquittal (Folder 2-3)
    - District Court orders and opinions
      - Post-trial (Folder 4)
      - Pretrial (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - Trial (Folder 2)
    - Court of Appeals opinions (Folder 3)
    - U.S. v. Nixon (Folder 4)
    - Nixon motions (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Broadcasting companies tapes suit (Folder 2)
    - Broadcasting companies tapes suit (contd.) (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Trial transcripts, 1974
      - Richard Ben-Veniste opening, Oct. 14. (Folder 2)
      - David Bress opening, Oct. 15. (Folder 3)
      - Jacob Stein opening, Oct. 16. (Box 49, Folder 1)
      - John Dean, Oct. 16-22. (Folder 2-8)
      - Dean, Oct. 23-34. (Box 50, Folder 1-2)
      - Cross-examination of Dean by Bress, Oct. 25. (Folder 3)
      - E. Howard Hunt, Oct. 28. (Folder 4)
      - Jeb S. Magruder and in camera, Nov. 1. (Folder 5)
      - Tapes authentication (contd.); proof of perjuries; Powell Moore, Nov. 7. (Box 51, Folder 1)
      - Excerpts relating to tape objections and Mardian references, Nov. 7-20. (Folder 2)
      - Moore (contd.); Grand Jury Chairman; Alexander Butterfield (resumed), Nov. 8. (Folder 3)
      - Vernon A. Walters; L. Patrick Gray III; Joan Hall, Nov. 11. (Folder 4)
      - Herbert W. Kalmbach, Nov. 12. (Folder 5)
      - Anthony T. Ulasewicz, Fred LaRue, Nov. 13. (Box 52, Folder 1)
      - LaRue (contd.); Walters (contd.), Nov. 14. (Folder 2)
      - Walters (contd.), Nov. 15. (Folder 3)
      - Thomas Green relating to Reisner train schedule; arguments; SSC testimony of John Ehrlichman and John Mitchell; tapes, Nov. 18. (Folder 4)
      - Thomas Green arguments on tapes; instructions relating to co-conspirators rule; William O. Bittman, Nov. 19. (Box 53, Folder 1)
      - Thomas Green objections and cautionary instruction relating to tape; Bittman, Nov. 20. (Folder 2)
      - Tapes; Haldeman video tape; Fred Fielding; Hunt, Nov. 21. (Folder 3)
      - Anthony J. Passaretti chart, Hunt, Egil Krogh, Nov. 22. (Folder 4)
      - Krogh, Passaretti; Motion for acquittal, Nov. 25. (Folder 5)
      - Cross-examination of John Mitchell by Thomas Green, Nov. 27. (Folder 6)
      - Ehrlichman on tapes referring to Mardian, Dec. 9-12. (Box 54, Folder 1)
      - Mardian witnesses and Mardian testimony, Dec. 13. (Folder 2)
      - Mardian testimony, Dec. 16. (Folder 3)
      - Mardian, Parkinson, Dec. 17. (Box 55, Folder 1)
      - Parkinson, Dec. 18. (Folder 2)
      - Parkinson, government rebuttal, James Neal closing, Dec. 19. (Folder 3)
      - Green motion on Canon 4, Dec. 23, 26. (Folder 4)
      - Green closing, Dec. 26. (Folder 5)
      - Stein closing, Neal rebuttal, Dec. 27. (Folder 6)
      - Instructions to jury, Dec. 30. (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Directing Robert Mardian to testify before the Grand Jury, 1973 May 7 (Folder 2)
  - Appeal (Case #1194)
    - Index (Folder 3)
    - Case summaries (Folder 4-6)
    - Pleadings (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Mardian briefs (Folder 2)
    - Other appellants briefs (Box 58, Folder 1-2)
    - Other appellants briefs (contd.) (Box 59, Folder 1-2)
    - Argument notes (Folder 3)
    - Legal research notes (Box 60, Folder 1-2)
    - Record notes (Folder 3)
    - Record notes (contd.) (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Articles (Folder 2)
    - Articles (contd.) (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Oral argument preparation (Folder 2)
    - Oral argument preparation (contd.) (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Oral argument (Folder 2)
    - Appendix. Tape transcripts
      - Volumes 1-2 (Folder 3-4)
      - Volume 3 (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - Decisions in other cases (Folder 2)
    - Reply brief
      - Legal research and notes (Folder 3)
      - Early drafts (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Duplicate copies of documents included in Joint Appendix (Folder 2)
    - Joint Appendix
      - Volume 1 (Folder 3)
      - Volume 2 (Box 66, Folder 1)
      - Volumes 1-2 (duplicates?) (Folder 2-3)
      - Draft (?) (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - New trial motions (Folder 2-3)
  - Related cases
    - General. Includes Lippman v. Mitchell et al., as well as disbarment proceedings against Robert Mardian (Box 68, Folder 1-6)
    - Mardian claims against the 1972 campaign trust liquidation (DGO32)
      - General. Correspondence, notes, memoranda, and miscellany (Folder 7-9)
      - General (contd.) (Box 69, Folder 1-4)
      - General (contd.). Primarily correspondence (Box 70, Folder 1)
      - Trust instruments (Folder 2)
      - Federal Election Commission reports filed by trust (Folder 3-5)
      - Memoranda and correspondence (Box 71, Folder 1-2)
      - Notes and memoranda (Folder 3)
      - Background material; submission to the trust (Folder 4)
      - Other drafts (Folder 5)
      - Research. Statute of limitations (Box 72, Folder 1)
      - Carson case (Folder 2)
      - Research. Trust-beneficiary relationships (Folder 3)
      - Parkinson; employee issue (Folder 4)
      - Ulasewicz lawsuit (Folder 5)
      - Liddy claim (Folder 6)
      - Submissions to trust (Folder 7)
- 1989 Increment, 1969-1986 (Boxes 73-82)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, notes, legal documents, speeches, printed material and miscellany. Primarily relates to Watergate-related trials and Justice Department files.
- Audiovisual File, 1973 (Tape cabinet)
  Videocassettes.
  - Seven video cassettes of Robert Mardian's testimony before the Senate Watergate Committee, 1973 July
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1968-1971
  - 2018 release of declassified records, 1968-1971 (Reading room workstation)